Guide to the Sam Dolgoff Papers TAM.093
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sam Dolgoff Papers
1874-1991, (Bulk 1937-1977)
1937-1977
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dolgoff, Sam, 1902-1990
TAM.093
0.75 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Sam Dolgoff (1902-1990) was an anarchist author and editor born Sholem Dolgopolsky in Byelorussia. He emigrated to the United States prior to World War I and joined the Young Peoples Socialist League in 1917 and the IWO in 1922. He served on the editorial board of Spanish Revolution, and wrote for other anarcho-syndicalist publications, often under the pseudonym Sam Weiner. He was a leading figure in the Libertarian Book Club, and wrote or edited several books until the late 1980s. The collection contains: unpublished and published writings by Dolgoff and other anarchists, including Mikhail Bakunin, Max Nettlau, and Rudolf Rocker; a collection of documents and ephemera by Cuban anarchists; and published biographical sketches of anarchists and other radicals. Much of the material concerns anarchism in Spain.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sam Dolgoff, 1984. The accession number associated with this gift is 1991.001.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sam Dolgoff (1902-1990), anarchist author and editor, was born Sholem Dolgopolsky in Byelorussia and emigrated with his family to the United States prior to World War I. He joined the Young Peoples Socialist League in 1917 and, as an anarchist, the Industrial Workers of the World in 1922. In 1925 he moved to Chicago where he joined the Free Society Group and later met his companion Esther Miller. Returning to New York in the 1930s, he served on the editorial board of Spanish Revolution, and wrote for and helped edit several anarcho-syndicalist publications, often using the pseudonym Sam Weiner. After World War II, he became a leading figure in the Libertarian Book Club, documented the suppression of Cuban anarchists in the years following the 1959 Cuban revolution, and wrote or edited several books, including The Anarchist Collectives: Workers' Self-Management in the Spanish Revolution, 1936-1939 (1974), Bakunin on Anarchy: Selected Works by the Activist-Founder of World Anarchism (1972), The Cuban Revolution: A Critical Perspective (1976), and Fragments: A Memoir (1986).
Bibliography
The American labor movement: a new beginning / Sam Dolgoff. Champaign, Ill.: Resurgence, 1980. 79 p.
The anarchist collectives; workers' self-management in the Spanish Revolution, 1936-1939. Introductory essay by Murray Bookchin. [1st ed. New York] Free Life Editions [1974] 192 p.
Bakunin on anarchy; selected works by the activist-founder of world anarchism. Edited, translated and with an introd. by Sam Dolgoff. Pref. by Paul Avrich. [1st ed.] New York, A. A. Knopf, 1972. 405 p.
Beware, anarchist!: a life for freedom: an autobiography / Augustin Souchy; translated & intoduced by Theo Waldinger; edited by Sam Dolgoff & Richard Ellington; with an afterword by Sam Dolgoff. Chicago: Charles H. Kerr Pub. Co., 1992. 247 p.
The Cuban revolution: a critical perspective / by Sam Dolgoff. Montreal Black Rose Books, c1976. 199 p.
Fragments: a memoir / by Sam Dolgoff. Cambridge [Cambridgeshire]: Refract Publications, 1986. 200 p.
The Labor Party Illusion. New York: Libertarian League, 1961. 1 v. Sam Weiner is a pseudonym of Sam Dolgoff.
The relevance of anarchism to modern society / Sam Dolgoff. 3rd rev. ed. Chicago: C.H. Kerr Pub. Co., 1989. 35 p.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is arranged alphabetically and contains unpublished and published writings by Dolgoff and other anarchists, including Mikhail Bakunin, Max Nettlau, and Rudolf Rocker; "The Last Maximalist: An Interview with Klara Klebhanova," by Dolgoff; a small but rich collection of documents, ephemera and publications by Cuban and Cuban-exile anarchists protesting (in English and Spanish), and some similar materials by Latin American and Spanish anarchists; conference papers on self-management; and a thick file of published biographical sketches of anarchists and other radicals (half in French, half in Spanish). Much of the material concerns anarchism in Spain during the Spanish Republic and Spanish Civil War, including Frank Mintz' 1967 book-length unpublished thesis, "La Collectivisation en Espagne de 1936 a 1939," subsequently published in revised form as L'Autogestion dans l'Espagne Revolutionnaire (1970).
Arrangement
The files are grouped into one series.
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Writings (document genre); Cuba -- History -- Revolution, 1959.; Anarchists |z Cuba |x History |y 20th century.; Anarchism |z Cuba |x History |y 20th century.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Proceedings.; Printed ephemera.; Biographies.; Documents.; Dolgoff, Sam, 1902-1990
- Container list
  - Sam Dolgoff Biographical Materials (obituaries, etc.), 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 0.1)
  - Avrich, Paul: "Lavrov and Russian Anarchism" (ts, 3pp), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commission of International Anarchist Relations: Bulletin of the Congress Commission, Dec 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cuba: English Language Documents, Ephemera, Publications by Cuban and Cuban-Exile Anarchists & Others (including SD), 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cuba: Movimiento Libertario Cubano En El Exilio, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cuba: Spanish Language Documents, Ephemera, Publications by Cuban and Cuban-Exile Anarchists & Others, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: Anarchism (notes), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: "Anarchism - Marxism" (incomplete, untitled ts, pp 2-18), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: "Constructive Anarchism in Spain" (ts, chapter-length), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: "Ballobar" (ms re this Spanish village), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: "Esplus" (ms re this Spanish village), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: Hungarian Uprising (notes), ca.1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: "To the Editor of the University Review" (ts, re SD's Bakunin book), ca.1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dolgoff/Bakunin: Letters to SD With Copies & Translations of Bakunin Letters, 1874-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - English Language Anarchist Documents, Ephemera, Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Espagne '62 (by the group Noir et Rouge, Paris), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gony, Harry: "A Taste of Paradise," "The Assassins of a Revolution" (ts, Spanish Civil War Memoirs), ca.1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Graphic Art Clippings & Postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Last Maximalist: An Interview with Klara Klebhanova (by SD; ts, 12 pp), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mintz, Frank: "La Collectivisation en Espagne de 1936 a 1939" (ts, 175 pp); Essai de Bibliographie sur la Collectivisation" (ts, 56 pp). Memoire (aka thesis), Institute d'Etudes Hispaniques (Paris)., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Montseny, Federica: "Autopsy of a Revolution" (ts, from Reconstruir, Buenos Aires - translated by SD?), Apr 1975-May 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Nettlau, Max: "The Libertarian Spirit in Spain from 1931 to 1933" (ms, 1 p, photocopy), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Biographical Sketches of Anarchists and Other Radicals (approximately 50 published unbound sketches, half are in French, half are in Spanish), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Radical Decentralist Project: Resolution #2" (ts, re Students for a Democratic Society), May 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rocker, Rudolf: "Road to the Third Kingdom" (ts, pp 193-211, from RR's book Nationalism and Culture), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Self-Management: Conference Papers and Articles (not SD), 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Spain: Anarchist Documents, Ephemera, Publications, 1937-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Spanish Language Anarchist Documents, Ephemera, Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Three Main Reasons for Our Defeat" (ms: SD translation of portions of "Why We Lost the War" by Diego A. De Santillan, Buenos Aires, 1940), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)